嗨大家好，歡迎來到入門 Python 教學，本系列特別專注於影像處理。在這段影片中，我們將..
hi everyone welcome to introductory python tutorials with a special focus on image processing in this video let's
使用我們在之前的視頻中開發的單元來執行二元語義分割
perform the binary semantic segmentation using the unit we have developed in the previous video
如果你還沒看過那個視頻，我強烈建議你去看一下
so if you haven't watched that i definitely recommend you to watch it
因為我們將使用完全相同的單元，這個單元是使用編碼器區塊的函數構建的
because we're going to use exactly the same unit that we built using functions for encoder blocks
和解碼區塊
and decoded blocks
在上一個視頻中可以
okay in the last video
然後我們將執行二元語義分割
and then we are going to perform a binary semantic segmentation
那麼我們所說的二進位語意分割是什麼呢？我想這很清楚
so what do we mean by binary semantic segmentation i think it's pretty clear
但如果不清楚，我們假設你有一張圖片在左側，物體
but if not let's say you have an image on the left hand side here the object
是要分割線粒體
is to segment the mitochondria
背景之外
out of the background
這個繁忙的背景之外
out of this busy background
這就是二進位
so this is binary
因為只有兩件事我在乎，一個是背景
because there are only two things i care about one background
另一個是線粒體
and the other mitochondria
我只希望這兩件事能分開
i only want these two things to be separated
事實上，我只希望線粒體能夠分開
in fact i only want the mitochondria to be separated
所以二元問題實際上是
so a binary problem is actually
一個問題
a problem
哪裡
where
你專注於一種單一類型的物件
you are focused on one single type of object
二進位給人一種印象
binary gives the impression that
好的，你需要兩個不同的東西，但二進位制基本上是你需要一個輸出
okay you need two different things but binary is basically you need one output
一個像素屬於線粒體像素的概率是多少
what is the probability that a pixel belongs to a pixel of mitochondria
或
or
它屬於背景，所以你需要一個輸出
it belongs to the background that's it so you need one output
如果該輸出顯示為 0.1
if that output says 0.1
然後我將設置一個閾值為 0.5
then i'll apply a threshold at 0.5
並說它低於 0.5
and say it's below 0.5
所以它必須是背景
so it must be background
如果超過 0.5，那一定是線粒體，就是這麼簡單
if it's above 0.5 it must be mitochondria that's it it's as simple
好的
okay
所以這就是所謂的二進位語意分割
so that's what a binary semantic segmentation
這就是我們如何建立一個單位
is and again we saw that this is how we can build a unit
我們在這裡討論的是，你看到的是 con 2d 的輸出層
and all we're talking about here is you see the output layer of con 2d
你在這裡有一個，這就是我們實際獲得的輸出
you have one right there this is the one output that we are actually getting right here
這就是二元的
this is what a binary
分割基本上意味著你有一個輸出就在那裡
segmentation basically means you have one output right there
好的
okay
和
and
哦，對不起，我應該提到這一點，我們使用的是 sigmoid 激活函數
oh sorry i should have mentioned this one output we are using sigmoid activation
那什麼是 sigmoid？回到視頻中
and what is sigmoid again go back to the video
我在其中講過這個，但簡單解釋一下
where i talked about it but a quick explanation
這是一個介於零和一之間的東西，可以把它想像成一種機率
this is a it goes between zero to one think of it as a probability
使用 Sigmoid 函數
using sigmoid function
你會得到一個概率
you get a probability
就在那時，你可以設定一個閾值
right there and then you say you can set a threshold
說如果概率低於 0.5
saying hey if the probability is below 0.5
如果它高於 0.5，我會稱之為背景
i'm going to call it background if it's above 0.5
這再次是我的線粒體
this is again my mitochondria
再次，我知道我在重複某些事情
again i know i'm repeating certain things
但這些在涉及到
but these are very very important when it comes to
你知道這個話題現在
you know this topic right now
好的，我們開始進入代碼部分
okay let's jump into the code
現在讓這變得有點有趣
and make this a bit fun right now
一如既往
as usual
我會分享程式碼
i'll share the code
所以再一次，請專注於我在這裡嘗試做的事情
so again please focus on what i'm trying to do right here
所以在 Google Colab 中，第一步你可以做任何事
so step number one in google collab you can do whatever
我正在您的本地電腦上顯示
i'm showing on your local computer
但
but
如果你有好的 GPU，就是那種你知道的
if you have good gpu that's you know with
一切安裝順利，否則嘗試使用 Colab
everything installed great otherwise try to use collab
因為您不需要擔心
because you don't have to worry about
安裝 GPU
gpus installing
然後首先更改運行時類型，它已經是 GPU
and all that so first of all change the runtime type it's already gpu
所以我沒問題
so i'm good
並讓我繼續連接
and let me go ahead and connect
並且它只允許您一次只使用一個 GPU
and it only allows you to work with one gpu at a time
您不能在多個 Colab 帳戶上運行
you cannot run on multiple colab accounts
你知道使用多個 GPU
you know with multiple gpus
所以
so
要注意這點
be aware of that
和你本地電腦一樣，如果你的 GPU 已經忙於處理
and same with your local computer right if your gpu is already busy doing
訓練模型不像你可以，你可以
training a model it's not like you can you can
編程它去做其他任務，那你的效率就會大幅下降，基本上是類似的
program it to do other tasks then your efficiency goes down pretty much similar
好的
okay
現在
so now
什麼數據
what data
我將要使用
am i going to work with
這裡的數據
this is the data here
請點擊這個鏈接，我會分享這個
go ahead and click on this link i'll share this
這會帶你到一個看起來像這樣的頁面，這是電子顯微鏡數據集
and it takes you to a page that looks like this this is electron microscopy data set
他們擁有原始圖像
and they have both the you know the original images
以及標籤
and also the labels
然後繼續下載它 下載
and go ahead and download it download
是的，每一個這些子卷
yeah each of these sub volumes
而我只處理第一個
and i'm only working with the first one
並且我拍攝了這些圖片
and i took these images
和面具
and masks
我已經將它們裁剪成
and i have cropped them into
成為
into
讓我們看看我在這裡做了什麼
let's see what am i doing here
轉換為 256 x 256 的大小。
into size of 256 by 256.
我實際上將這些圖片裁剪成 256x256
i actually cropped these images into 256x256
如果你問我怎麼做的，我一直在講解 patchify
if you ask me how did i do that i've been talking about patchify
和 unpatchify 已經有一段時間了，對吧
and unpatchify for a while right
我的意思是使用名為 patchify 的函式庫
i mean use the library called patchify
這可以實際從你的圖像中生成區塊
that can actually generate patches out of your images
然後只需寫幾行代碼將這些圖像保存為 JPEG 格式
and then just write a couple of lines to save those images as jpegs
將提示或提示保存到本地磁碟
or tips onto your local drive
如果你
if you
如果你想，你可以編寫那段代碼
if you want you can code that
我的意思是這並不難對吧？我的意思是你加載一個任意大小的 numpy 陣列
i mean that's not difficult right i mean you load a numpy array of whatever size
然後你說我想把這個分成 256 x 256 的區塊。
and then you say i want to divide this into 256 by 256.
所以繼續，每次在 x 和 y 方向上取 256。
so go ahead and get 256 at a time in x and y
然後就保存到你的硬碟，別忘了完全按照步驟做。
and then just save it to your drive don't forget to do exactly
與你的遮罩相同
the same to your masks
因此你的輸入影像
so your input images
和遮罩明顯地匹配在一起，你不希望出現不匹配的情況
and masks kind of match together obviously you don't want a mismatch
好的
yeah
所以我
so i
我相信在這種情況下我使用了 patchify
believe in this case i used patchify
然後我說，好吧，這是我的大圖像，進行切片
and i said okay this is my large image patchify it
所以如果我的圖像是 7，我不知道 512 乘 512，那麼
so if my image is 7 i don't know 512 by 512 then
如果我將其切割成 256，那麼我將得到
if i chop it into 256 then i'll get
2 乘 2 乘 256 乘 256，對吧
2 by 2 by 256 by 256 right
希望這樣能說明清楚
i hope that makes sense
好的
okay
所以 5 12 在 x 5 12 在 y，所以是 2 乘 2
so 5 12 in x 5 12 in y so it's 2 by 2
我保存了這四個
and i saved these four
將我的 5 12 乘以 5 12 的四個補丁轉移到我的本地驅動器上
four patches from my 5 12 by 5 12 on to my local drive
然後我對我的面具做了相同的操作
and then i did the same for my masks
所以這就是我如何從這裡獲得我的數據集
so that's how i got my data set from here
現在我有了我的 256 x 256，讓我們繼續
now that i have my 256 by 256 let's go ahead
並開始工作
and start working
好的，讓我們導入所需的庫
okay let's import the required libraries
我不認為我在使用 normalize
i'm i don't think i'm using normalize
有些這些你會發現
some of these i you'll realize
我並沒有使用
that i'm not using
它們，但它們是剩下的
them but they are left over from
從我之前的實驗中
from my earlier experiments
但我傾向於保留它們，以防你想使用 normalize
but i tend to leave them in in case you want to use normalize
在你知道如何縮放你的影像時
in you know to scale your images
嗯，我就這樣留著吧
yeah so i'll just leave that
好的，讓我們來檢查這些檔案 opencv
okay os to walk through the files opencv
使用 pillow 來調整圖像大小
pillow to resize images
如果你需要
if you have to
numpy 陣列
numpy array
顯然這就是我們正在使用的 piplot，我也留了這個 min max scaler
obviously is what we are working with piplot i also left this min max scalar
如果你想用這個來縮放圖像而不是標準化
if you want to use this to scale images instead of normalize
這取決於你
it's up to you
而從優化器中我正在導入 atoms
and from optimizers i'm importing atoms
所以我們可以把它當作優化器來使用
so we can use that as an optimizer
我正在使用 glob
and i'm using glob
這樣我們就可以遍歷檔案
so we can walk through the files
好的，請原諒我
okay excuse me
現在我正在定義我的影像和遮罩目錄
now i'm defining my image and mask directory
我已經，讓我檢查，我已經連接了我的驅動器，就在那裡，Google Drive
i have already let me check i have already connected my drive right there google drive
然後我所做的就是去我的數據所在的地方
and all i did is go to my data wherever the data is
然後只需
and then just
然後只需複製此路徑
and then just get this copy path
是的，這正是
yeah that's exactly
我所做的
what i've done
這是我的圖片路徑，這是我的遮罩路徑
and this is the path to my images this is the path to my masks
所以這只是定義目錄，接下來我會定義大小
so this is just defining the directories next i'll define the size
和圖片數量
and number of images
我想合作的是因為這次我分開
i'd like to work with because this once i divide
我想我最終得到了大約 1600 張圖片
this i think i ended up with about 1600 images
然後訓練變得有點慢
and then the training gets a bit slow
當然，我建議你使用全部 1600 張圖片。就我而言，我只
of course i recommend you to use all 1600 images in my case i just
選擇使用，我不知道，500 張圖片
chose to use i don't know 500 images
或 1000 張
or thousand
然後我停在了一千
and i stopped at thousand
因為我得到了不錯的結果
because i was getting decent results
所以我們繼續，這些只是變數對吧
so let's go ahead and these are just variables right
所以現在我們需要定義
so now we need to define
我的圖像名稱
my image names
你如何定義你的圖像名稱
how do you define your image names
好吧，首先為什麼我
well why first of all why am i
定義圖像名稱，而不僅僅是從磁碟中加載圖像
defining image names and not just loading the images from the disk
問題在於這是另一個重要的建議
the problem is this is again another important piece of advice
在您花費大量時間加載圖像之前
before you spend a lot of time when you load the images
就直接一個接一個地載入，就像寫一個 for 迴圈一樣
just go ahead and load one after the other like just write a for loop
好的
yeah
然後從特定磁碟中一個接一個地加載
and then load one after the other from a specific drive
問題是，在 Windows 上它可能運作良好
the problem is on windows it may work fine
因為 Windows 可能會根據這些數字進行整理
because windows probably organizes these based on the number
或其他什麼
or something
但在 Linux 上肯定會是這樣
but on linux like definitely here
如果你這麼做，它很可能
if you do that it's it's probably
你的圖片會根據它被加入到硬碟的時間來排序
your images are sorted based on the time it got added to the drive
然後當你載入你的圖片時
then when you load your images
而且你的遮罩會對不上
and your masks they won't line up
因為當你加載第一張圖片為 500 多時
because when you load the first image as 500 something
但是第一個遮罩有 100 多，他們對不齊
but first mask has 100 something they don't line up
所以我們需要根據名稱對圖片進行排序
so we need to sort images based on the names
或任何我們需要排序的標準
or whatever criteria we need to sort them
兩張圖片
both images
和面具，假設你的面具
and masks assuming your masks
和圖片有類似的名稱，例如如果我的圖片是 image 121
and images have similar names like if my image is image 121
我的面具將會是 mask 121，對吧？這是處理你的圖片和面具的最佳方式
my mask will be mask 121 right that's the best way to do your images
和面具，我希望這樣解釋清楚了
and masks i hope i hope this makes sense
所以要整理我的圖片
so to sort my images
首先讓我獲取圖片的名稱
first let me get the names of the images
然後
and then
我會進行排序
i'll sort
好的
okay
所以首先我們來查看一下
so let's check out first of all
glob dot glob 這會顯示檔案的名稱
glob dot glob it gets you the names file names of what
所有具有 TIFF 擴展名的文件
everything that has an extension of tiff
所以讓我們繼續載入它
so let's go ahead and load that
並列印名稱，讓我們繼續這樣做
and print the names let's go ahead and do that
所以它正在載入，正在讀取所有檔案以獲取名稱
so it's loading it's reading all the files getting the names
只是列印名稱
and just printing the names
我只是想給你看看
i just want to show you
這些名稱如何是隨機的，你看我的第一張圖片是 602.tiff
how these names can be random you see my first image is 602.tiff
我的下一張圖片如果我往右移動到那裡
my next image if i move right there
是 601.f
is 601.f
然後是 600.f
and then 600.f
所有 fsn604.tiff
all fsn604.tiff
如果我離開
and if i go
這不是，這不是在六四十八的順序，如果我來這裡
it's not it's not in an order six forty eight if i go here
我有一一六七一一七二
i have one one six seven one one seven two
完全不同的一些隨機順序
completely different some random order
所以我想要這些被排序
so i want these to be sorted
我該怎麼做
how do i do that
所以我拿我的圖像名稱
so i take my image names
然後我只是做點排序
and i just do dot sort
現在我們來打印它
now let's go ahead and print it
你會看到圖像 0
and you see image 0
希望它應該是圖像 1 圖像 2
hopefully it should be image 1 image 2
所以我的意思是 1 之後是從 10 開始的
so i mean after 1 it starts with 10 right there
然後是 11
and then it's 11
或 100
or 100
一千，從這個開始，很明顯首先查看這個
one thousand it's starting with it's obviously looking at this one first
好的
yeah
然後它會到達兩個，我打賭
and then it goes to two i bet
所以
so
然後一千二，一千三，一千四
and then one thousand two one thousand three one thousand four
然後它會跳過
so on and then it jumps
所以這有一個特定的順序，這就是我想說的全部
so there is a specific order to this that's it that's all i'm trying to say
所以這些圖像中，我只會取前 1000 張，我有 1600 張
so of these images i'm going to take only the first 1000 images i have 1600
或其他什麼
or something
所以讓我再拍攝 1,000 張圖片，為什麼
so let me just take 1 000 images again why
因為我希望我的訓練能稍微快一點，這是可選的
because i want my training to be a bit faster this is optional
好的，一旦我做到這點
okay once i do that
現在是閱讀圖像的時候
now is the time to read the images
到目前為止，我有影像名稱，但在陣列中沒有影像
so far i have image names i don't have images in the arrays
所以目前我要讀取的方式，你也可以使用數據生成器
so the way i'm going to read at this point you can also use a data generator
所以你會批次讀取影像，我們將來會做一個相關的視頻
so you read images in batches we'll do a video on that in future
但現在我們將所有一千張圖像載入記憶體中
but for now we are loading all thousand images into the memory
然後進行訓練
and then performing the training
好的
okay
我們怎麼做到這一點
how do we do that this is a a
對於列表推導式，就像你知道的，對於這些圖像名稱子集中的每個圖像
for list comprehension like you know for each image in these image name subset
就在那裡，對於這些圖像中的每一個，繼續使用 cv2.imread
right there for each of these images go ahead and do cv2.imread
以及每個影像
and each image
然後將其讀取為一個正確的灰階影像
and then read that as a grayscale image that's exactly
這行正在做的事情，這會非常慢
what this line is doing this will be very slow
因為現在它正在讀取 1000 張圖像
because now it's reading 1000 images
好的
okay
當它在執行這個操作時，讓我們繼續前進
and while it's doing that let's go ahead
並查看面具部分，我對面具做了完全相同的操作，我正在讀取
and look at the masks part i'm doing exactly the same for masks i'm reading
所有的遮罩名稱
all the mask names
你看到 glob 點 glob
you see glob dot glob
然後我正在整理它們
and then i'm sorting them
這一步非常重要
and this step is very important
如果你想要這些影像
if you want these images
和面具以完全相同的方式進行排序
and masks to be sorted exactly the same way
所以你的影像
so your images
和遮罩會排列整齊
and masks will be lined up
好的，再說一次，當事情不如預期時，你會失去理智
okay again you'll lose your mind when things don't work out that way
而且要花很長時間才能弄清楚到底為什麼
and it takes forever to figure out exactly why
好的
okay
然後來到面罩名稱零到一千，這就是我們已經完成的
and then comes mask name zero to one thousand that's what we have already done
然後是 cb2.imread
and then comes cb2.imread
所以這些步驟與我對我的圖像所做的完全相同，對吧
so these steps are identical to what i have done with my images right
除非我把所有東西都放在一個區塊中
except i just put everything in one block
所以一旦圖像變紅
so once the images are red
這將是一個列表
this will be a list
這些是影像的列表，我將它們轉換為 numpy 陣列
right these are list of images i convert them to numpy array
然後我擴展維度
and then i expand the dimensions
使它們處於正確的格式
so they are in the right format
用於我的神經網絡
for my neural network
好的
okay
所以這就是我們在這裡嘗試做的事情
so that's that's what we are trying to do here
我的遮罩也是一樣
and same with my same with my masks
然後我將在這裡列印出形狀
and then i'm going to print out the shapes right here
所以
so
我會再說一次，我不確定這還要花多久時間
what i'll do is again i'm not sure how much longer this is going to take
那我現在暫停這段影片
so let me pause this video right now
等我們準備好影像後再繼續
and continue as soon as we have the images ready
好的，已經過了三到四分鐘
well it's been three to four minutes
這個還在載入中
and this thing is still loading
所以我們來停止它，因為我已經訓練好了模型
so let's go ahead and stop it because i've already trained the model
所以讓我把這個改成 100 張圖片
so let me change this to 100 images
所以我們可以測試模型對吧
so we can test the model right
所以我們先把這個改成 100 張圖片
so let's go ahead and change that to 100 images
和
and
現在我們來讀取這 100 張圖片
now let's read these 100 images
我希望這將比閱讀 1000 張圖片快得多
and i hope this will be much much faster than reading 1000 images
所以希望它可以在幾秒鐘內完成
so hopefully it should be done in a few seconds
然後我們可以繼續
and we can continue
因為我們需要一些測試用的圖片
because we need some images for testing
好的
okay
所以我已經用 1000 張圖片訓練了一個模型
so i've already trained a model using 1000 images
好的
okay
所以
so
現在讓我們將那些轉換為 numpy 區域
now let's convert those into numpy areas
否則這些圖像只是一堆列表對吧
because otherwise these images are just a bunch a list right
所以讓我們轉換它
so let's convert that
然後擴展尺寸
and then expand the dimensions
現在讓我們對我們的面具做完全相同的操作
now let's do exactly the same for our masks
這應該會非常快速
and this again should be pretty fast
就這樣閱讀這 100 個面具
there you go reading these 100 masks
隨時應該就會完成
and anytime it should be done
然後我們就可以重新開始了
and then we are back in business
好的
okay
現在我們繼續
so now let's go ahead
並且列印出我們影像遮罩的形狀
and print out the shape of our images masks
和
and
影像中的最大像素值是多少
what is the maximum pixel value in the image
以及遮罩中的標籤
and also the labels in the masks
好的，我們會看看為什麼這些很重要
okay we will see why these are important
所以
so
我們來打印這些，所以我們應該會有 100 張圖片，很明顯我們把數量從 1000 改為 100
let's print these so we should have 100 images obviously we changed from 1000 to 100
所以這就是每張影像所代表的，每張影像是 256 乘 256 乘 1
so that's what that represents each image is 256 by 256 by one
而那個 1 是因為它是灰階影像，我們
and that one is because it's a grayscale image and we
對於遮罩，我們也有差不多相同的
also have pretty much the same for masks
現在最大像素值為 255
now maximum pixel value is 255
在我們的圖像中
in our images
因為我們尚未進行正規化
because we haven't normalized
或縮放
or scaled
或將標籤圖像輸入到遮罩中，標籤也為 0
or input images the labels in the mask are also 0
並且 255 0 對應於背景
and 255 0 corresponds to the background
這是黑色背景
which is the black background
和 255 對應於這些明亮的圖像，這正是
and 255 corresponds to these bright images that's exactly
他們如何提供他們的數據集
how they provided their data set
標籤 0 到 55 沒有問題
nothing wrong with label 0 to 55
我喜歡將標籤設定為 0 1 2 3。
i like the labels to be 0 1 2 3.
所以我將這個除以 255，同樣也將這個除以 255。
so i'm going to divide this by 255 also divide this by 255
所以我們有了縮放。
so we have scaling
您可以選擇使用最小最大標準化，而不是進行分割
instead of dividing you can also do min max scalar
或規範這些東西
or normalize any of those things
所以我選擇了簡單的方法，這樣就可以了
so but i chose the easy way this works fine
是將我的影像數據集和匹配數據集除以 255。這樣就好了
is divide my image data set and match dataset by 255. there you go
現在我們的值將會是 0
and now our values will be just 0
或者 1 來對應我的遮罩
or 1 for my mask
和 0 到 1
and 0 to 1
用於我的圖像
for my images
到目前為止，一切順利，我們還沒做太多事情，我們只是
so far so good again we haven't done much of anything we just
整理了我們的圖像
sorted our images
並以排序後的順序載入了前 100 張圖像
and loaded the first 100 images in in that sorted order
和我們的面具一樣
and same with our masks
然後我們意識到我們的圖像
and then we realized our images
和面具需要調整大小
and masks need to be scaled
然後我們把它們除以 255 學校來縮放，僅此而已
and then we just divided them by 255 school to scale them that's it
現在我正在劃分我的圖像
now i'm dividing my images
和掩碼成 80 用於訓練，20 用於測試
and masks into 80 for training 20 for testing
好的
okay
那麼我們就去做這個，即使我們不打算進行訓練
so let's go ahead and do that even though we're not gonna train
我這麼做的原因是進行一次基本檢查總是個好主意，這意味著
the reason i'm doing that is it's always good idea to perform a sanity check meaning
嘿，生成一個介於 0 到 100 之間的隨機數字，在這個情況下
hey generate a random number between 0 to 100 in this case
或 99
or 99
並繪製或標記你的圖像
and map out or plot your images
和面具
and masks
查看它們是否對齊，這正是
see if they're lining up that's exactly
我在這裡嘗試做的
what i'm trying to do here
如果它們對齊，那我就可以開始了，所以這看起來非常好
if they line up i'm good to go right so that looks very good
這看起來像那些圖片
that looks like the images
以及面具，讓我們載入另一張隨機圖片，沒有問題，太好了
and masks let's load another random image nothing there great
好的
okay
所以一切都對應上了，這點非常重要，因為
so everything is matching up this is this is very important to do because
你正在從磁碟載入資料對吧
you're loading data from the disk right
然後繼續進行
so and then go ahead
並定義你的模型，我們在上一個影片中已經講解過這一點
and define your model we covered this in the last video
正確定義卷積區塊，定義編碼器區塊
right defining the convolution block defining the encoder block
這兩個
which gives you these two
和解碼器
and a decoder
塊，這是我們的模型
block and this is our model
我不想浪費你的時間來講這些
again i don't want to waste your time by going through this
因為我們在上一個影片中花了半小時談論這個
because we spent half an hour talking about this in the last video
好的
okay
我們定義了這個模型
so we defined this model
當我調用它時，它會返回這個模型
and when i call it it's going to return this model
那麼我該如何調用它呢
so how do i call it well
在哪裡給它輸入形狀
where is it give it input shape
和類別數量正確
and number of classes right
我們還添加了這些行
and we also added these lines
如果我的類別數量不是二元的
so if my number of classes are not binary
那麼它將使用 softmax
then it's going to use softmax
如果是二元的
if it is binary
意味著類別數量等於一，記住二進位
meaning number of classes equals to one remember binary
這並不意味著兩個二進位代表一個輸出
doesn't mean two binary means one output
是的，那麼它將使用 sigmoid
yeah then it's going to use sigmoid
所以我的輸入維度
so my input dimensions
或者輸入形狀是我的圖像高度寬度
or input shape is my image height width
以及通道數量
and number of channels
即 256 到 56 1.
which is 256 to 56 1.
所以讓我們繼續定義這個
so let's go ahead and define that
然後建立模型
and then build the model
非常簡單，你提供這個
very simple you provide this
然後我們將使用 Adam 作為優化器來編譯模型
and then we are going to compile the model by using adam as our optimizer
二元交叉熵 這是一個二元語義分割
binary cross entropy this is a binary semantic segmentation
和指標 我們將使用準確度來訓練指標 就像我說的 交集
and metrics we are going to use accuracy to train the metrics again like i said intersection
聯合度是一個更好的指標來追蹤
over union is a better metric to track
對於語義分割，我們會在未來涵蓋這個主題
for semantic segmentation we'll cover that in future
但準確度有效，並不是那樣的
but accuracy works it's not like it
但它只是不告訴你有多好
but it just doesn't tell you how good the
這裡在我的時期中，1 項中的 25 項，真是太好了
how good it is because here in my epoch 1 out of 25
或
or
時期一，是的，這是我的時期一中的 50 項中的一項，我應該這麼說
epoch one yeah this is my epoch one out of 50. i should say
我做了多少個時期，抱歉，我做了 25 個時期
how many epochs did i do sorry i did 25 epochs
這 50 個是 50 次迭代
and these 50 are 50 iterations
所以 1/25
so 1 out of 25
在第一個時期準確度對驗證來說很差，而在第二個時期為 92
in the first epoch the accuracy was bad for validation in the second epoch it's 92
突然之間
all of a sudden
那這是好還是壞呢？
but is that good or bad
我們不知道，對吧？我的意思是，這就是精確度的問題所在
we don't know right i mean this is what the problem is with accuracy
所以當我往下走時，我的準確率是 99%
so as i go down i got 99 accuracy
但交集
but intersection
與聯集將會找到
over union will find
判斷它是好還是壞，然後我保存了我的模型
out if it is good or bad and then i saved my model
好的
okay
現在我們下去吧
now let's go down
這就是圖表的樣子
and this is how the plots look like
那麼我們繼續前進
and let's go ahead
並載入模型
and load the model
我們將其儲存為這個名稱，所以我們繼續
so we saved this under this name so let's go ahead
並載入模型，我將設置 compile 為 false
and load the model i'm going to put compile equals to false
因為我不再進行進一步的訓練，我只是用這個模型來進行推斷，就這樣
because i'm not further training using this i'm just using the model for inference that's it
好的
okay
以及交集比率（Intersection over Union，IoU）計算
and for intersection over union calculation
我的意思是你可以追蹤交集佔並集比例
i mean you can track intersection over union
這是你應該在每個時代（epoch）進行的操作
which is what you should do for every epoch
而這僅在
and that only happens
如果你把交集與聯合比作為你在這裡追蹤的指標之一
if you put that intersection over union as part of your metrics that you're tracking here
但完成後，你可以計算整個數據集的交集與聯合比
but once it's done you can calculate intersection over union over your entire data
這就是我們在這裡嘗試做的
that's what we are trying to do down here
首先，我們需要進行預測
first of all we need to predict
在我們的測試數據集上
on our test data set
好的
yeah
所以我們來進行預測，在我們的情況下，測試數據集只有 20 張圖片
so let's go ahead and predict in our case our test data set is only 20 images
因為我們只讀取了幾百個，我應該更改過來，但讓我們檢查一下我們的 model.predict
because we only are reading hundred i should have changed that but let's check our model.predict
你怎麼預測
how do you predict
model.predict，再次說明這與分類相同，沒關係，始終是 model.predict
model.predict again this is same as in classification it doesn't matter it's always model.predict
我在我的 x 測試數據集中進行預測，那是 20 張圖像
and i'm predicting on my x test data set that's 20 images
然後我將應用 0.5 的閾值
and then i'm going to apply a threshold of 0.5
這意味著它會轉換
which means it converts
每個值的機率
every value probability
因為當你執行 model.predict 時，它會給你 sigmoid
because when you do model.predict it's going to give you sigmoid
我一直回到基本概念，但這些非常重要
i keep going back to the basics here but again these are very important
我們正在使用 你正在使用
we are using you're using
激活函數為 sigmoid
activation function as sigmoid
在這裡，sigmoid 函數會給出介於 0
right here a sigmoid gives you probability between 0
和 1
and 1
這意味著我們需要將那個概率轉換成類別
which means we have to convert that probability into class
而那就是
and that's
我們就用我們的閾值來做這件事
what we do with our threshold right there
好的
okay
我們將放入每個值
so we are going to put every value
預測值超過 0.5
predicted value above 0.5
我會稱它為線粒體
i'm going to call it mitochondria
那就是這樣
that's what that is
所以我們來計算交集與聯合比率，你可以進行導入
so let's calculate intersection over union the way you do that is go ahead and import
從 keras.metrics 導入 iou
mean iou from keras.metrics
並應用這個，這僅適用於 TensorFlow
and apply that and this only works on tensorflow
2 及之後，之前你沒有那個意思的 IOU
2 and later before that you don't have that mean iou
所以可能會引發一些錯誤
so it may throw some error
希望你們都在使用 TensorFlow 2 或更高版本
okay hopefully you're all working on tensorflow 2 or later
因此，對於 IoU 計算，我會說我的類別數量等於 2
so and for iou calculations i'm going to say my number of classes equals to 2
因為我有 0
because i have 0
和 1. 這可能會令人困惑
and 1. this may be confusing
但對於 Keras 的 IOU，你有 2 0
but for keras iou you have 2 0
和一個
and one
所以它會看起來好，你有零
so it's going to look at okay you have zero
和一個
and one
那麼讓我計算 IOU，這就是它在做的事
so let me calculate iou that's what this is doing
所以你在這裡用類別數來實例化平均 IOU
so you instantiate mean iou right there with number of classes
然後你使用從這裡得到的預測值來更新其狀態
and then you update the status of that using your predicted values from here
我將使用閾值
i'm going to use the thresholded
然後是測試值對吧
and then the test values right
所以
so
然後繼續打印結果
and then go ahead and print the result
所以之前用我不確定的 200 張圖片，我得到 91 的 IoU
so previously with my i don't know 200 images i got 91 iou
這非常棒，我應該說平均 IoU 是 92，這很棒，意味著
which is excellent by the way i should say mean iou 92 great that means
這個線粒體的交並比
the the intersection over union for this mitochondria
背景的交並比達到 92％
and the background we have 92 percent you know for that
對於語義分割，任何超過 90 的交並比都是優秀的
and anything above 90 for semantic segmentation iou is excellent
那麼我們設定 0.5 作為閾值
so let us set a threshold of 0.5
而這部分的代碼基本上是載入圖像
and do exactly this part of the code is basically loading an image
希望是一張隨機圖像，就在那裡
hopefully a random image yeah right there
從我們的測試數據集中加載一個隨機圖像
so loading a random image from our test data set
然後預測
and then predicting
和列印，就是這樣繪圖
and printing that's it plotting
那我們來做吧
so let's do that
這裡沒什麼好看的
not much to see here
我們再試一次，希望能成功
let's run it one more time hopefully
我們會得到更好的影像
we'll get a better image
天啊，我們有所有空白的圖片，這是你的測試標籤
god we have all empty images there you go this is your testing label
這是我們得到的結果
this is what we got
預測結果並不那麼驚人
the prediction isn't that amazing
非常好的分段
very good segmentation
沒有任何內容
nothing there
我們有許多空的數據集，這也不算壞
we have many many empty data sets that is also not bad
讓我們把這個改為 x train
let's change this to x train
因為我們在訓練中有更多的數據
because we have more data in the train
我們繼續檢查一下，你也可以載入外部
and let's go ahead and check it you can also load external
圖像來檢查情況
image to check things out
好的
yeah
所以那就是
so there you go that's
我的意思是，這並不完美
i mean it's not perfect
但這不是壞的分段，它正在檢測
but that's not bad segmentation it is detecting
粒線體
mitochondria
啊，我覺得
ah i think
哦，我應該說 x 列減一，抱歉
oh i should have said x train minus one sorry
好了，就這樣
okay there you go
稍微好一些會更好
a little bit it can be better
再來一次
and one final time
是的，我們已經看過這個了
yeah we already saw this
所以我不確定
so i'm not sure
為什麼它沒有查看測試編號
why it's not looking at test number
但這沒問題
but this is fine
x 測試，讓我們在之前改為測試
x test let's change this to test before
我會與你分享代碼，不然你會想知道為什麼我在使用 train
i share the code with you otherwise you'll be wondering why i'm using train
好的，我保證不再多說
okay i promise no more more
好，讓我們以這個結尾吧
yeah let's let's end on this note
那我們學到了什麼
so what did we learn
一旦你定義了你的單位
once you define your unit
這非常簡單，其餘的都是數據處理
it's very easy everything else is data handling
你只需將數據劃分為額外的索引測試
you just divide your data into extra index test
傳遞給你的單元
pass it to your unit
讓單位發揮其魔力
let unit do its magic
然後通常它在下一個視頻中表現出色，讓我們看看多類別
and then usually it works great in the next video let's look at multi-class
這與二分類略有不同
which is slightly different from binary
因為你必須將圖像轉換為類別
because you have to convert your images to categorical
除此之外，其他一切都相同，我們將使用完全相同的
other than that everything else is the same we are going to use exactly the same
模型
model
所以無論你在使用什麼，你都有一個通用模型
so you have one universal model no matter what you're working with
好的
okay
所以
so
再次在下個影片中見面
again let's meet again in the next
影片，直到那時不要忘記訂閱這個頻道，謝謝大家
video until then do not forget to subscribe to this channel thank you guys